<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Plato on </title>
    <link>/PhilosophyNotes/tags/plato/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Plato on </description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 17:06:20 -0400</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="/PhilosophyNotes/tags/plato/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Plato Republic Book 1 and 2</title>
      <link>/PhilosophyNotes/posts/plato-republic-book-1-and-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2024 17:06:20 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/PhilosophyNotes/posts/plato-republic-book-1-and-2/</guid>
      <description>&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-warning-to-those-who-are-reading-these-notes&#34;&gt;A warning to those who are reading these notes.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the following notes are going to be rough. They are shortened, often not proper, but are trying to pull out main concepts.
This is more for me to have a place to dump notes and keep them in a central place where it&amp;rsquo;s not prone to my ineptitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been wanting to read this book for a long time. In college, I only read sections that were relevant to specific topics or concepts that classes found useful. While I learned concepts from it, I never got a chance to grasp the book itself.
To take this book at least halfway through, I am looking at a series of lectures in a Yale online course that talks about this book. I will also be referencing Gregory Sadlers core concepts to pull out any other information that I might miss throughout the books.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content>&lt;h1 id=&#34;a-warning-to-those-who-are-reading-these-notes&#34;&gt;A warning to those who are reading these notes.&lt;/h1&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All of the following notes are going to be rough. They are shortened, often not proper, but are trying to pull out main concepts.
This is more for me to have a place to dump notes and keep them in a central place where it&amp;rsquo;s not prone to my ineptitude.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;introduction&#34;&gt;Introduction&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been wanting to read this book for a long time. In college, I only read sections that were relevant to specific topics or concepts that classes found useful. While I learned concepts from it, I never got a chance to grasp the book itself.
To take this book at least halfway through, I am looking at a series of lectures in a Yale online course that talks about this book. I will also be referencing Gregory Sadlers core concepts to pull out any other information that I might miss throughout the books.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&#34;yale-notes&#34;&gt;Yale Notes&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a book about a place called Kallipolis. It&amp;rsquo;s a just and beautiful city ruled by philosopher kings. What is the republic about? What does it deal with?
Is it a book about justice? Is it about moral psychology and the ordering of the human soul? Is it a book about the power of poetry and myth, which is culture? Is it a book about metaphysics and being?
It&amp;rsquo;s about all of these things, at the beginning it&amp;rsquo;s best to stay on the surface. The surface of the republic is a conversation. We approach the book as a work of literature or drama. The author asks us to be active participants in this dialogue.
The republic is a utopia. It&amp;rsquo;s an extreme vision of politics and the polis. The guiding thread of the book is the symmetry between the parts of the city and the parts of the soul. Discord in the city and soul is seen as the greatest evil. Kallipolis means to harmonize the soul and city.
It seeks to achieve this with the highest type of individual. Any city will have issues unless there are philosopher kings. The republic asks us to consider what would a city look like ruled by philosophers. It is a response to the Apology, an experience of the dangers of the city towards the philosopher.
What would it look like for a philosopher to rule the city? Censorship of poetry and theology, the abolition of private property and the family, and the use of selected lies and myths/ideology as tools for political rule. The republic represents some dystopia.
Most political science is against Plato&amp;rsquo;s Republic. Our society is based on private life being separate from the state.
Plato&amp;rsquo;s Republic recognizes no such separation. Some critique it as a totalitarian state. This was popularized by Karl Popper, in the open society and its enemies.
He viewed Plato principally as the first to establish a totalitarian dictatorship. Is that true? It&amp;rsquo;s not one intended to maximize individual liberty, but one that takes the education of the individual as its highest priority.
Its principal goal is the education of citizens for positions of public leadership and high responsibilities.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He regards the politea/regime as a chief goal towards guiding civil society. It&amp;rsquo;s not a political treaty, but the most beautiful work on education - Rousseau.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;i-went-down-to-the-piraeus&#34;&gt;I went down to the Piraeus&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does Plato begin with this line? What does it mean? Heidegger spent a whole semester not getting past that line. The Greek word for going down - Catabasis. The Greek word for going up - Anabasis. He begins with this descent, its modeled on Odysseus&amp;rsquo;s descent to Hades. It&amp;rsquo;s a kind of philosophical odyssey.
It&amp;rsquo;s full of descents and ascents. The most famous climb is the divided line, the ascent to the world of forms. The last book is a decent to the underworld, hades. It&amp;rsquo;s a dramatic dialogue with a firm location, time, and place.
Plato was born in 427 4 years after the Peloponnesian War. He was 28 when democracy was restored. Immediately after the trials of Socrates, he traveled the Greek world and established a school for training statesmen, philosophers, and legislators.
The republic belongs to that period of work after Plato returns to Athens after Socrates&amp;rsquo; execution. David Green said the root and branch character of change it advocates and existing institutions. His desire for radical change is because of these massive defeats and disillusionment with the experience of the Athenian polis.
Plato is not a participant but is an author. In the seventh letter, he establishes they are his and gives us an autobiography and why he wrote the republic.
He says when he was young he felt he should engage in public affairs, and had an opportunity. The democracy was abolished and the leaders set themselves up as a government of 30 men. Some of them were relatives of Plato. They invited him to join as if he were a fit match. He was young and thought the political life was unjust, and
if rules were bent they could be just. He locked on those who made the former democracy look like a golden era.
The older I grew the more difficult it seemed for me to administer politics justly. It is hard to find others who are just. As eager as he was to join and try to help, he felt overwhelmed. He did not abandon his interest or opportunity but saw that all states are poorly governed. I was compelled to say that it was from philosophy alone we could discern justice.
He saw rulers needed to either be philosophers or one must come to intertwine with philosophy.
This provides an introduction to the republic. We can understand his approach and disillusionment, its dialogue points back to an earlier moment of life. The action of the republic took place before the defeat of Athens, 30 years earlier, and made democracy look like a golden age.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&#34;analyzing-the-beginning-and-the-hierarchy-of-characters&#34;&gt;Analyzing the Beginning and the Hierarchy of Characters&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Socrates and his friend Glaucon trolling the Piraeus/Harbor, What are they doing there? What do they expect to find? They took this way to view a festival/carnival. A new goddess is being introduced, it&amp;rsquo;s not Socrates but Athenians who create new deities. Socrates remarked that Thracians put on a good show. On their way back, they&amp;rsquo;re accosted by a slave who has been sent by
Polemarchus and his friends. He orders them to wait. When they arrive they are greeted by Adeimantus, who is Glaucon’s brother, and Niceratus, who is the son of Nicias, the general who has just brokered the peace that they are now enjoying. That’s the famous Peace of Nicias. They tell them they have to join them because they are simply outnumbered. Socrates tries to ask if they will listen to reason.
The response is, not if we ignore you. They go to Polemarchus&amp;rsquo; home after this short swift conflict between reason and numbers in terms of what&amp;rsquo;s just. Who has the title to rule on this occasion? Can democracy be rendered compatible with the needs of philosophy? This is the question of the opening scene.
Is the just city, a combination of both force and persuasion. The first book is a preamble to everything.
There are a large number of characters but very few of them actively speak at this dinner party. Who are they and what do they represent?
Cephalus, the father of Polemarchus, whose home they are in. Polemarchus is a patriot who defends his father&amp;rsquo;s honor. Thrasymachus is a cynical intellectual who rivals Socrates as a future leader and statemen.
There is a hierarchy of characters. They each represent characteristics of the soul and city. &amp;ldquo;Cephalus, we learn, has spent his life in the acquisitive arts. That is to say, he’s a businessman. He’s been concerned with satisfying the needs of his body and making money. He represents what will later be called in the Republic the appetitive part of the soul, the appetites. Polemarchus, whose name means “warlord.” Think of that. The warlord is preoccupied with questions of honor and loyalty. He tells us, to get a little bit ahead of ourselves, that justice is helping your friends and harming your enemies. He seems to represent what Plato or Socrates would later call the spirited part of the soul, something that we want to return to. Thrasymachus, a visiting sophist, seeks to teach and educate, anticipating what the Republic will call the rational soul, the rational part of the soul.&amp;rdquo;
The two brothers Glaucon and Adiomantus,  who are brothers of Plato, represent something quite different. Adeimantus is hedonistic, Glaucon means something like gleaming, is the fierce and war-like of the two brothers.
Its appetitive, war-like, and rational are seen as the spirit of humanity. Each participant represents a group/class that exists in the beautiful city/Kallipolis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first conversation with Cephalus. The question he wants to examine is what these characters represent. Cephalus is &amp;ldquo;head&amp;rdquo;, age tradition, and family.  When we see Cephalus returning from prayer, he greets Socrates as a long-lost friend—a slightly uncomfortable one. Socrates does something abrupt, Socrates asks what it is like to be old and do they still want to have sex. Cephalus is happy because he says he is past it. He can spend his time/twilight turning to the things that support the gods. Why does Plato begin this way? He is the embodiment of the convention. He is a thoroughly unreflective man. Socrates attacks the embodiment of conventional opinion. Note how he manipulates the dialogue.
Cephalus says justice is when you worship and sacrifice to the gods. Socrates turns that into the statement that justice means paying your debts and returning what you owe. Cephalus agrees and asks what if you borrow a weapon from a depressed friend, and you need to give it back. Would you do it if justice meant paying your debts? Cephalus excuses himself and says I have to go out and continue my sacrifices. Socrates broke the bond of tradition and traditional authority. Cephales is banished from this dialogue.
That&amp;rsquo;s how Socrates begins this dialogue.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;republic-book-1&#34;&gt;Republic: Book 1&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;h2 id=&#34;republic-book-2&#34;&gt;Republic: Book 2&lt;/h2&gt;
</content>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
